Guide to the Radio Haiti Audio Recordings, 1957-2003 RL.10059
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Radio Haiti audio recordings
1957-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Radio Haiti-Inter
RL.10059
100 Linear Feet
Audio recordings from Radio Haiti-Inter, documenting Haitian politics and culture from 1957 to 2003 (bulk 1972-2003). Under the leadership of station directors Jean Dominique and Michèle Montas, Radio Haiti was a voice of social change and democracy, speaking out against oppression and impunity while advocating for human rights and celebrating Haitian culture and heritage.
Documents sonores de Radio Haïti-Inter, documentant la politique et la culture haïtienne de 1957 à 2003 (majorité 1972-2003). Sous la direction de Jean Dominique et Michèle Montas, Radio Haïti fut une voix du changement social et de la démocratie, dénonçant l'oppression et l'impunité tout en défendant les droits humains et célébrant la culture et le patrimoine d'Haïti.
Dokiman sonò Radyo Ayiti-Entè, ki reprezante politik ak kilti ayisyen soti nan 1957 rive nan 2003 (pi fò se 1972-2003). Anba direksyon Jean Dominique ak Michèle Montas, Radyo Ayitite yon vwa chanjman sosyal ak demokrasi, ki te denonse tout kalite opresyon ak enpinite pandan li te defande dwa moun epi selebre kilti ak patrimwan ayisyen.
Arrangement / Classement / Ki jan yo klase
Recordings are arranged chronologically within alphabetized program categories.
Les enregistrements sont classés en ordre chronologique.
Anrejistreman yo nan lòd kwonolojik.
Provenance / Kote koleksyon an soti
The Radio Haiti collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
La collection de Radio Haïti a été reçue par la David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library comme un don en 2013.
Koleksyon Radyo Ayiti te yon don ke David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library jwenn nan 2013.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, and tapes have been digitized. Digital access to the Radio Haiti audio is provided through the Duke Digital Repository: https://repository.duke.edu/dc/radiohaiti. For audio resources listed in this guide that are not yet in the Duke Digital Repository, and for other access requests, please contact Research Services staff.
Restrictions à l'accès
La collection est ouvert à la recherche. L'accès numérique est fourni par cet instrument de recherche. Pour toute autre demande, veuillez communiquer avec le personnel de Services de Recherche (Research Services).
Restriksyon sou aksè achiv yo
Koleksyon an ouvè pou moun ka fè rechèch ladan l. Nou ka jwenn dokiman dijital atravè gid rechèch dijital sa a. Si nou gen lòt demann, tanpri kontakte manm staf Sèvis Rechèch (Research Services).
Collection Overview / Aperçu de la collection / Yon ti chema koleksyon an
The Radio Haiti audio collection spans 1957 to 2003 (bulk 1972-2003) and consists of open reel and cassette audio recordings. With the exception of a very small number of recordings that are restricted to protect the identities of the speakers, the entire audio collection is digitized and publicly available.
The Radio Haiti collection is perhaps the most thorough documentation of late 20th century Haitian politics and history, including but not limited to the Duvalier regime and its aftermath; the nascent democratic movement amid military rule under the Conseil National de Gouvernement in the late 1980s; the first presidency, overthrow, return, and second presidency of Jean-Bertrand Aristide; the aftermath of the 1991-1994 coup years during which Haiti's democratically-elected government was in exile; and the first presidency of René Préval. Radio Haiti both covered and spoke out against impunity, calling for justice for victims of human rights violations and political oppression as well as victims of corruption and corporate malfeasance. With his background as an agronomist, Jean Dominique focused in particular on the political and land rights of dispossessed peasant farmers and the need for Haiti to strengthen and support national agricultural production. Radio Haiti advocated for freedom of the press and documented repression of the independent media, covered grassroots organizations and women's rights campaigns. Radio Haiti covered international relations, including the plight of undocumented Haitian refugees fleeing to the United States or the Bahamas (so-called "boat people"), Haitian cane-cutters in the Dominican Republic and repatriations of Haitian people from the Dominican Republic, US policy toward Haiti and US involvement in Haitian politics, neoliberal reform and structural adjustment policies. Radio Haiti promoted and showcased Haitian art and culture, including painting and sculpture, literature, poetry, theatre, music, history and national heritage, and other intellectual production. They highlighted Vodou as a meaningful and important part of national culture worthy serious analysis. The station focused extensively on key moments of repression and injustice, such as the 1987 Jean Rabel massacre of peasant farmers and the 1994 Raboteau massacre of Aristide partisans by the military and FRAPH paramilitary, and on important assassinations and disappearances, including but certainly not limited to liberation theology priests Jean-Marie Vincent and Jean "Ti Jan" Pierre-Louis, and, of course, the hired killing of Radio Haiti's own director, Jean Léopold Dominique.
Radio Haiti afforded as much consideration and airtime to the voices and concerns of peasant farmers from rural Haiti, members of grassroots organizations, Haitian braceros living on Dominican bateys, and residents of poor urban neighborhoods as it did to prominent politicians and intellectuals. By reporting largely in Haitian Creole, the language that all Haitians speak and understand, Radio Haiti made media and communication truly democratic, and showed Creole could be a language of serious political and intellectual inquiry.
Radio Haiti's programming consisted of on-the-ground breaking news, reportage, extensive on-air interviews and debates (such as "Face à l'Opinion", "Pawòl la Pale" and "Forum Electoral"), news magazines (such as "Inter-Actualités Magazine" and "Inter-Face"), cultural programming ("Entre Nous") and editorials ("Le Point"). The collection was acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive.
Description of the audio is in progress and therefore not all titles listed here have been verified. Consequently some of the titles in this guide may not reflect actual tape content.
The Radio Haiti audio tapes have been digitized and many are available in the Duke Digital Repository: https://repository.duke.edu/dc/radiohaiti. For help accessing files not yet in the Repository, or for any questions regarding recording content, please contact Rubenstein Research Services staff.
For the Radio Haiti Papers, see Guide to the Radio Haiti Papers
Biographical / Historical Note
Radio Haïti-Inter, the first independent radio station in Haiti, was remarkable for its broad democratic appeal and unparalleled popularity with the Haitian people. Founded in 1935 by Haitian radio pioneer Ricardo Widmaier as an entertainment medium, Radio Haiti came into its own in the late 1960s, when prominent and outspoken agronomist-turned-journalist Jean Dominique bought the station.
Dominique had been arrested and forced to leave his post as an agronomist in the northern part of the country during the early years of the Duvalier dictatorship. Seeking work in Port-au-Prince in the mid-1960s, he began anchoring cultural programs and talk shows on Radio Haiti's airwaves. By 1971, when he rechristened the station Radio Haïti-Inter, Dominique had begun to transform it into a powerful instrument of resistance to dictatorial rule and political corruption. During the 1970s, Radio Haïti-Inter was the sole station providing news and commentary in Creole, the language of the majority of Haitians, as well as in French, which – despite being understood by less than 10% of the population – was the traditional language of the media.
The decades covered by the archive were tumultuous ones in Haiti. As the country was buffeted by the tides of political strife and instability, so too was the station. On November 28, 1980, the Duvalier regime undertook a massive campaign of repression against journalists, human rights advocates and nascent opposition parties. All of Radio Haïti's reporters were arrested. Most were jailed and later sent into exile in the US, Venezuela and Canada. Some were tortured, such as station manager Richard Brisson, who was ultimately executed by the regime in 1982.
Dominique narrowly escaped and fled to Caracas, then later to New York, where he was reunited with his wife and professional partner, Michèle Montas, who was forcibly exiled there after her release from prison. When the Duvalier regime fell in 1986, the couple immediately returned to Port-au-Prince to rebuild the station with funds raised from the Haitian people. During the tumultuous transition years under various military regimes in the late 1980s, the station was attacked several times; its façade bore the scars of bullets and grenades. Nonetheless, Radio Haïti remained on the frontlines of the fight for free expression, opening its microphones to the previously voiceless and sending reporters into the countryside and crime-ravaged "no-go" areas of Port-au-Prince.
The station was forced to close again in 1991 when the elected government of Jean Bertrand Aristide was overthrown by a military coup after only seven months in power. Dominique and Montas fled once more into exile, returning in 1994 when U.S. troops invaded Haiti and re-instated Aristide. As he had throughout his career, Dominique remained unwavering in his efforts to unearth and report government corruption and human rights abuses.
On April 3, 2000, Jean Dominique and station employee Jean Claude Louissaint were murdered by hired gunmen in the courtyard of Radio Haiti. Montas, along with Dominique's daughter, journalist Jan (J.J.) Dominique, who had been the executive director of the station since 1994, continued Jean's quest for truth and justice and kept the station open. The team of young, courageous and dedicated reporters remained on board and, despite constant danger, redoubled their commitment to justice and human rights issues. They pursued in-depth investigations into unpunished crimes, in particular an investigation into the controversial and highly political circumstances of Dominique's assassination. After an attempt on Montas' life in 2002, during which her bodyguard, Maxime Seide, was gunned down, and amid escalating threats against the station's staff, Michèle Montas and J.J. Dominique closed the station in February 2003, and again went into exile.
During its history, Radio Haiti Inter broadcast daily from 6am to midnight and offered hourly five-minute news summaries, six one-hour news programs (three in Creole, and three in French), an afternoon feature program (Micro Témoin /French), as well as a one-hour round table or interview program in either French or Creole (Forum démocratique, Pawòl la Pale or Face à l'Opinion) depending on the season. It also hosted a number of educational programs on health, women's rights, and agriculture. Over its three decades of operation, the station was driven by the efforts and courage of impressive teams of reporters and correspondents. Montas, who worked first in the 1970s as a reporter and investigative journalist, headed the newsroom from 1990 to 2003 and trained several generations of Haitian journalists during her thirty-year career. Marcus Garcia later founded Radio Mélodie.Konpè Filo (real name Anthony Pascal) is a journalist and well known radio and TV personality. Liliane Pierre-Paul,Marvel Dandin, and Sony Bastien, founded Radio Kiskeya, a station that to this day continues Radio Haiti's commitment to public interest programming. Harold Isaac, chief editor at the time of the 1980 crackdown, resettled in Canada after his forced exile. J.J. Dominique anchored the daily "Micro Témoin" and the cultural magazine "Entre Nous," and is now a well-known writer in Montreal. Pierre Emmanuel served as chief editor of the newsroom from 1990 t0 2003, and is currently a broadcast journalist in Montreal. That same period saw the efforts of reporters such as Jean Roland Chery, Immacula Placide, and Guerby Dujour. Paul Dubois oversaw cultural programming. Sony Esteus headed the Sosyete Animasyon ak Kominikasyon Sosyal, a network of community radio stations in Haiti, until his death in 2015. Gregory Casimir and Fritzson Orius have since founded their own radio stations.
These individuals and many other staff members possessed the high journalistic standards and fierce commitment to in-depth reporting that were the hallmark of Radio Haiti's broadcasts. Through daily coverage of events, interviews with major writers, artists and thinkers, political analysis, and roundtable discussions on Haiti's history and culture, Radio Haiti's staff brought together a collection of voices and perspectives that constitutes perhaps the most important and complete single archive of late 20th century Haitian history. These recordings also bear witness to the evolution of Haitian society and media over more than thirty years. In the 1960s and 1970s, newspapers and the few existing radio stations published and broadcast primarily in French, while Creole, the language of the majority of Haitians, was relegated to advertising, music and entertainment. As new media outlets emerged after the fall of Duvalier and as technological innovation made radio accessible to all, the media landscape changed dramatically. Today, news coverage in Creole is far more prevalent; the majority of Haitians, at last, can understand and be heard on the news. Radio Haiti pioneered and actively shaped this change.
The Radio Haïti archives extend over a wide breadth of material, ranging from cultural programming during the 1970s and early interviews on haïtianité or "what it means to be Haitian" — often with intellectuals and conducted in French — to Creole-language reportage and debates during the period 1986 to 2003 when the concerns and voices of masses, at last, featured prominently on the airwaves. In short, these recordings serve as testimony to a difficult and too often bloody battle for freedom of speech and freedom of association, led by Radio Haiti and Haitian civil society.
The lives of Jean Dominique and Michèle Montas and the history of Radio Haiti are the subject of the 2003 documentary film, The Agronomist, produced by the award-winning film director, Jonathan Demme.
Note biographique / historique
Radio Haïti-Inter, qui fut la première station radio indépendante en Haïti, jouissait d'une popularité sans pareil parmi le peuple haïtien. Fondée en 1935 par Ricardo Widmaier, un innovateur dans le domaine de la radio, la station n'a véritablement trouvé son identité que lorsque Jean Dominique, agronome reconverti en journaliste, l'a rachetée à la fin des années 1960. Avant cela, Dominique travaillait comme agronome dans le Nord d'Haïti, jusqu'à ce qu'il soit arrêté par le régime des Duvalier et forcé de quitter son poste. Alors qu'il cherchait du travail à Port-au-Prince au milieu des années 1960, on lui a confié l'animation d'émissions culturelles sur les ondes de Radio Haïti.
En 1971, Dominique a rebaptisé la station radio Radio Haïti Inter, et c'est alors qu'il a commencé à transformer la radio en un outil de résistance majeur contre la domination dictatoriale et la corruption politique. Dans les années 1970, Radio Haïti était la seule station à transmettre et commenter l'actualité en créole (qui est la langue maternelle de tous les Haïtiens) en plus du français (le français était, à cette époque, la langue traditionnelle des médias en Haïti, même si moins de 10% de la population le comprend bien et le parle couramment).
L'époque couverte par les enregistrements fut marquée par l'agitation et la violence. Au même titre qu'Haïti, la station radio vivait au rythme des conflits et l'instabilité politiques. Le 28 novembre 1980, le régime des Duvalier lança une campagne de répression massive des journalistes, des militants des droits de l'homme et des partis de l'opposition. Tous les journalistes de Radio Haïti furent arrêtés. La plupart furent envoyés en prison, puis exilés de force aux États-Unis, au Venezuela ou au Canada. Certains furent torturés, comme Richard Brisson, le gérant de la station, qui fut finalement exécuté par le régime en 1982.
Dominique réussit à s'échapper et à s'enfuir à Caracas, puis New York. C'est là qu'il retrouvaMichèle Montas, son épouse et associée, qui y avait été exilée de force après sa sortie de prison. A la chute du régime des Duvalier en 1986, le couple retourna immédiatement à Port-au-Prince pour reconstruire la station de radio, projet rendu possible notamment grâce à l'argent donné par le peuple haïtien. La station radio fut attaquée à de multiples reprises pendant les années de transition qui virent se succéder plusieurs régimes militaires à la fin des années 1980. Sa façade fut criblée de balles et de traces de grenades. Malgré cela, Radio Haïti resta sur la ligne de front du combat pour la liberté d'expression, donnant le micro à ceux qui n'avaient pas de voix et envoyant des reporters dans la campagne et les quartiers « chauds » de Port-au-Prince, où personne n'osait aller.
La station fut forcée de fermer à nouveau en 1991 quand un coup d'état renversa le gouvernement de Jean-Bertrand Aristide après seulement 7 mois passés au pouvoir. Dominique et Montas furent obligés de repartir en exil aux Etats-Unis. Ils rentrèrent en Haïti en 1994 quand les soldats américains envahirent le pays pour rétablir Aristide comme président. Comme il l'avait toujours fait pendant sa carrière, Dominique continua à travailler sans répit pour dénoncer la corruption gouvernementale et la violation des droits de l'homme.
Le 3 avril 2000, sa quête de la vérité et de la justice finit par lui coûter la vie. Jean Dominique fut abattu dans la cour de la station radio aux côtés d'un employé nommé Jean Claude Louissaint. Montas, accompagnée de la fille de Dominique, Jan (J.J.) Dominique, qui travaillait comme directrice exécutive de la station depuis 1994, décidèrent de garder la station ouverte. L'équipe de journalistes, tous jeunes, vaillants et dévoués, ne quittèrent pas le navire malgré le danger qu'ils encourraient, et redoublèrent d'effort pour faire triompher la justice et les droits de l'homme. Ils menèrent une enquête sur les crimes restés impunis, et se penchèrent en particulier sur les circonstances de l'assassinat de Jean Dominique. En 2002, une autre tentative d'assassinat à l'encontre de Michèle Montas entraîna la mort par balle de son garde du corps, Maxime Seide. Suite à la recrudescence et l'escalade de menaces à l'encontre des membres de la station radio, Michèle Montas et J.J. Dominique décidèrent de fermer la radio en février 2003 et de repartir à nouveau en exil.
Radio Haïti-Inter proposait des émissions quotidiennes, de 6h du matin à minuit. Elle offrait un résumé de 5 minutes de l'actualité une fois par heure, six programmes d'actualités d'une heure (trois en créole et trois en français), un programme dans l'après-midi sur un thème particulier (Micro Témoin, en français), ainsi qu'une table ronde d'une heure ou un programme d'entretiens en français ou créole (Forum démocratique, Pawòl la Pale or Face à l'Opinion) selon la saison. Il y avait aussi un programme éducatif sur la santé, le droit des femmes, et l'agriculture. En trente ans de travail, c'est vraiment le courage et les efforts de l'équipe de reporters et de correspondants qui permirent à la station de fonctionner. Montas, qui commença dans les années 1970 comme reporter et journaliste d'investigation, dirigea la rédaction de 1990 à 2003 et forma plusieurs générations de journalistes haïtiens pendant sa carrière. Marcus Garcia fonda Radio Mélodie. Konpè Filo (Anthony Pascal de son vrai nom) est un journaliste et personnage très connu dans le domaine de la radio et de la télévision. Liliane Pierre-Paul, Marvel Dandin, et Sony Bastien fondèrent Radio Kiskeya, une station qui existe toujours et qui continue l'engagement de Radio Haïti à servir l'intérêt général. Harold Isaac, qui était rédacteur en chef lors de la répression de 1980, est parti au Canada quand le gouvernement l'a forcé à quitter Haïti. J.J. Dominique présentait le programme quotidien « Micro Témoin » et le magazine culturel « Entre Nous ». Elle est à présent une écrivaine reconnue qui vit à Montréal. À la même période, la station radio appréciait également la présence à l'antenne et les efforts de journalistes comme Jean Roland Chery,Immacula Placide et Guerby Dujour. Paul Dubois était responsable de la programmation culturelle. Sony Estéus était responsable de la Société d'Animation et de Communication Sociale, un réseau de radios communautaires en Haïti, jusqu'à sa mort en 2015. Gregory Casimir et Fritzson Orius ont, depuis, aussi fondé leurs propres radios.
Ces personnes, et bien d'autres membres de l'équipe, possédaient tous les qualités journalistiques et l'engagement féroce pour le reportage en profondeur qui étaient la marque de fabrique de Radio Haïti. À travers la couverture quotidienne des événements, des entretiens avec d'éminents écrivains, artistes et penseurs, l'analyse politique et des discussions sous forme de table ronde, les journalistes de Radio Haïti ont réuni un ensemble de voix et d'opinions qui constituent peut-être l'archive la plus importante et la plus complète sur l'histoire d'Haïti à la fin du vingtième siècle.
Ces enregistrements montrent l'évolution de la société et des médias haïtiens sur une période de plus de trente ans. Dans les années 1960 et 1970, tous les journaux étaient publiés en français, et les quelques stations radio existantes émettaient en français également. Pendant ce temps, le créole n'était utilisé que dans les publicités, la musique et le divertissement, malgré le fait qu'elle soit la langue maternelle de la population et de tous les Haïtiens. De nouveaux médias sont apparus après la chute de Duvalier, et avec les innovations technologiques qui ont rendu la radio plus accessible à tous, le paysage médiatique a changé de façon radicale. Aujourd'hui, grâce à Radio Haïti qui fut précurseur et montra le chemin, la couverture de l'actualité en créole est bien plus répandue et la majorité des Haïtiens peuvent ainsi enfin comprendre les nouvelles et participer directement et faire entendre leur propre voix.
Les archives de Radio Haïti représentent une variété de matériel; des programmations culturelles datant des années 1970 et d'anciennes entretiens au sujet de « l'haïtianité » (ou « ce qu' "être Haïtien" signifie), bien souvent réalisés avec des intellectuels et en français, à des reportages en créole et des débats durant la période de 1986 à 2003 quand les intérêts et les voix du peuple haïtien ont réussi à être entendus à la radio. En bref, ces enregistrements sont le témoignage du combat difficile et trop souvent sanglant qu'ont mené Radio Haïti et la société civile haïtienne pour la liberté de parole et la liberté d'association en Haïti. Le documentaire L'Agronome, réalisé en 2003 par Jonathan Demme, cinéaste de renom, présente l'histoire de Radio Haïti-Inter ainsi que la politique haïtienne au vingtième siècle et la vie de Jean Dominique et Michèle Montas.
Nòt biyografik / istorik